<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached April, 8. 1635 At a visitation at Brentvvood in Essex. By Alexander Read, Doctor of Divinitie, late fellow of Pembroke-Hall in Cambridge, now Parson of Fifield in Essex.</title>
            <author>Read, Alexander, Doctor of Divinitie.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10507</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102936</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838696</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3084</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10507)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3084)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1151:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached April, 8. 1635 At a visitation at Brentvvood in Essex. By Alexander Read, Doctor of Divinitie, late fellow of Pembroke-Hall in Cambridge, now Parson of Fifield in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Read, Alexander, Doctor of Divinitie.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by B. Alsop and T. Fawcet] for Iohn Clark, and are to be sold at his shop under St. Peters Church in Cornehill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3084:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3084:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED APRIL, 8. 1635. AT A VISITATION AT BRENTVVOOD in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ALEXANDER READ. <hi>Doctor</hi> of Divinitie, late Fellow of <hi>Pembroke</hi>-Hall in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> now Parſon of <hi>Fifield</hi> in Eſſex.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="poem">
               <body>
                  <head>The Author to his Booke.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntimely birthes inherite not long breath.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>See and be ſeene, then dye a timely death.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>After a Moneth or two ſay nought of me:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Meane while goe witneſſe my Conformitie.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for IOHN CLARK, and are to be ſold at his Shop under St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornehill.</hi> 1636.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3084:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3084:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT A Viſitation at <hi>Brentwood</hi> in ESSEX.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. COR. 14.40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Let all things be done decently and in order.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Engliſh tranſlations differ in turning the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Some turne it <hi>by Order,</hi> ſome <hi>according to Order,</hi> and this is <hi>verbum verbe</hi> with the Greeke. Others, among
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3084:3"/>which is our laſt tranſlation, turne it <hi>In Order.</hi> Wherein they leave the Greek and follow the Syriac. It is frequent with the Syriac tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to borrow the Greeke word, ſo has hee done here. He borrowes the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and joynes it with the Hebrew prepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſteed of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in order,</hi> in ſteed of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>according to Order.</hi> But the ſence being the ſame I will inquire no further into the words, I come to the matter.</p>
            <p>I muſt not while I plead for decency and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, paſſe the bounds of decency and order.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould follow decency and order as farre as they goe, an age were fitter for my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe then an houre.</p>
            <p>The words <hi>Creature</hi> and <hi>Creation,</hi> are not ſo large as the words <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order;</hi> for as much as God himſelf fals within the compaſſe of order. <hi>Primum, ſecundum, tertium,</hi> are but ſo many linkes of the ſame order, and GOD is <hi>Primum Ens, primum Vivens, primum Momens &amp; ultimum. Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega.</hi> (Apoc. 1.8.)</p>
            <p>The whole Creature alſo (or as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PAVL cals it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the whole Creation) fals within the extent of <hi>Decencie and Order.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.22.</note> For that which wee ſay in Engliſh, <hi>GOD made all things in decency and order,</hi> is no other than that which MOSES in Hebrew ſayes, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.) — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then that which the Pen-man of the booke <hi>Wiſdeme</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3084:3"/>(whether PHILO IUD Aeus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sapient.</hi> 11.21 Engl. verſ. 17</note> or IESUS the ſonne of SYRAC, or who elſe) in Greek ſayes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thou haſt <hi>ordered</hi> all things in meaſure, number and weight, and This is Canonicall though the booke be Apochrypha.</p>
            <p>I will not therefore meddle with the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>natura,</hi> the <hi>Order</hi> of naturall things and comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them.</p>
            <p>Nor will I meddle with the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the dependency and correſpondency of Arts and Sciences in themſelves and their own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, or theyr mutuall helpes one to another and contatenations one with another: theyr mediocrities, proportions and lovely rules and fruites.</p>
            <p>Not will I intermeddle with bodies Civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politick or oeconomick. In all which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>Order</hi> is theyr ſtability and ſtrength, and <hi>Decency</hi> theyr comelineſſe and beauty.</p>
            <p>That which I will ſpend my time in, ſhall be the <hi>Decencie</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p>Nor will I take the whole Decency and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church to view. I will not looke how glorious the Kings daughter is within, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.13.) How comely in the eyes of God the Soule of man is, when the affections and paſſions are ordered by reaſon and reaſon by God,<note place="margin">Nagian. pag. <hi>110.</hi> li. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> when the whole man is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeakes. When mens
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3084:4"/>lives are lived out toward Heaven. When there is in the Soule of man an aſpiring ambition of comming neere the Angels in perfection, and the Saints and Martyrs in devotion.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Decencie</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> which I will now meddle with, is the <hi>Decencie</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of our publiqve Aſſemblies, and of thoſe, not in Councils and Synods, and Convacation-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or the like: but in that Houſe which is gloriouſly ſtyled by GOD <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (<hi>Eſa.</hi> 56.7.) The houſe of Prayer or materiall Temple.</p>
            <p>In theſe aſſemblies I will not inquire into the inward reverence done, nor ſit judge upon the Soules of men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stapl. tom.</hi> 2.707.</note> whether they doe <hi>Hoc agere</hi> or no. I will only lay before your view, the outward face and cariage of our Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>And (that yet I may bound my ſelfe narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) I will only diſcourſe of thoſe things which I am daily <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of; ſhewing only mine opinion, leaving the deciſion of judgement to you that have the Seats of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and becauſe the ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32.) To you alſo my brethren of the Clergie.</p>
            <p>I will begin with the <hi>Place</hi> of our Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies.</p>
            <p>While I ſpeake of the Place, underſtand me not of all the Churches in our land, wee have thoſe that are according to St. PAULS rule, Orderly and Decent, and which have accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3084:4"/>to our Canons framed themſelves into a blameleſſe beautifulneſſe, I ſpeake of ſome Churches only, and of ſome only would I be underſtood.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It ſeemes to me an <hi>vndecent thing,</hi> That places of Churches of late yeares fairely ceeled ſhould now have nothing left to defend, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the eye from offence or the floore from floods; but that wee may feare ſhortly leaſt <hi>navis Eccleſiae</hi> ſhould floate away in raine and ſnow water. ASAPH complained of the like above 2600 yeares agoe, whoſe ſpirit I deſire to be of in this age. <hi>Qui hoc habuit peculiare, ut de rebus Eccleſiae triſtibus meditaretur, Now they breake downe all the carved worke thereof with Axes and hammers.</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.6.) <hi>Calaturas ejus</hi> her ceelings.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſeems to me as <hi>vndecent,</hi> That Church-wainſcots, and perhaps the ſame, wrought with gold and divers colours by the penſill of the cunning limmer, ſhould now be a Sear for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men. Since it was a more noble imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them to be the common beauty of a Church, then to be the decking of a private Seat, and ſince <hi>Publica privatis ſunt anteponenda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 It ſeemes to me <hi>an undecent thing,</hi> Since PAUL is never the more payd by this robbing of PETER, that ſeates of the higheſt ranke ſhould by the Pariſhioners be kept, now full 4 yeares together in ſuch a condition, that the raine fals on theyr Bookes, on theyr tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3084:5"/>the Cuſhins and mats rot under them as they ſit, the boards are as white under theyr feet with mould, as a Swans-skin with feathers, the whole ſeat ſaving your preſence ſtinkes ſo, that 'tis fitter to be <hi>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſuis,</hi> then <hi>ſella venenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and ſo it is at this houre. <hi>Vndecent</hi> I ſay, ſince even the meaneſt in the Congregation ought to ſerve God windright and watertight. For howſoever in the Temple of SALOMON,<note place="margin">Godw Antiq. Hebr pag <hi>40.</hi> lin. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Laici the People,</hi> in faire weather did alwayes pray <hi>ſub dio</hi> &amp; <hi>teſte Caelo,</hi> in the open eye of Heaven: Yet had they their <hi>Porticus</hi> and ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to which they betooke themſelves to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip dry in time of raine. And thus much of the <hi>Place</hi> of our Aſſemblies. Now of ſome <hi>Vtenſils</hi> in it and things of affinitie in nature.</p>
            <p>And firſt of that which in all ages of the Church has beene counted (Gods booke only excepted) the moſt reverend and honourable, the Communion-table.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſeemes to me an <hi>undecent</hi> thing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt St. PAULS rule; That a Church ſhould have in it a Communion-table not worth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 12. or 14<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. at the moſt. Since of all the tables in the Pariſh that only has had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Greg. Nazian.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Morn. <hi>1.</hi> de Miſſ. <hi>375.</hi>
               </note> as the firſt Councill of <hi>Nice;</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as St. <hi>Paul.</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21.)</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſeemes to me an <hi>undecent</hi> thing, That our Communion bread, which is by and by to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3084:5"/>be the body of CHRIST, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be brought into our Church, and <hi>Sanctum Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> in a ſtain'd courſe totterd linnen poke, like <hi>adſit reverentia verbo,</hi> a pudding bag, or that (I may not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) a <hi>foule muckinger,</hi> &amp; therely all prayers time till Sermon begin, in the view of the Congregation to <hi>vileſcere in oculis popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li;</hi> ſince the very bringing of it into the Church to that uſe, is a taking of it out of the World, a promotion of it to more reverence, and a next ſtep to conſecration it ſelfe. Alſo, that a Church ſhould not have ſo much as a homely Napkin to cover it, or to take away in decent manner the fragments. Since all the inſtruments of the Tabernacle were by Gods owne appointment ſo curiouſly covered, even the candleſticks, ſnuffers and ſnuffediſhes, from the eyes of the Sonnes of <hi>Kohath</hi> with a cloth of blew ſilke when they were to remove the Tabernacle. <hi>Numb.</hi> 4.9.15.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It ſeemes to me an <hi>undecent thing.</hi> That many times the courſeneſſe of the bread and vappidneſſe and fouleneſſe of the the wine is ſuch, or of the bottles, that the eye makes the mouth loath to touch the cup, and <hi>extra ſacramentum,</hi> would rather drinke homely water. Since when GOD carved for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; he choſe out not onely the pure, but the pureſt; nor the fine, but the fineſt;<note n="a" place="margin">Exod 25.24</note> 
               <hi>aurum Puriſſimum,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 27.20.</note> 
               <hi>Oleum puriſſimum,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Levit. 24.6.</note> 
               <hi>Suffimentum
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3084:6"/>puriſſimum,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Num. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.9</note> 
               <hi>locum puriſſimum.</hi> For ſo the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tranſlation tranſlates the words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; I thinke he does not amiſſe in ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating it, for ſo I am ſure the ſenſe is; and the <hi>Simila,</hi> out of which the<note n="e" place="margin">Levit. 24, 5</note> 
               <hi>Panes Propoſitionis,</hi> were made to ſtand before the Lord, was the fineſt of the flowre, for the Sonnes<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ornel. a lap.</note> of <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hath</hi> (not the lay-people) made them and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them. 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.32. And they boulted out of ſo many peckes of meale but ſo many pottles; as <hi>Maimon</hi> reports in his <hi>Tamidin</hi> of dayly ſacrifices,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ainſworth</hi> on Levit. 24, 5</note> and this muſt bee no other but the fineſt. And ſince God has made the fine and pure, why ſhould man ſerve him up to his owne Table the <hi>faces,</hi> the foule and courſe. Thus of the firſt <hi>Vtenſil,</hi> the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table, and ſome undecencies about it.</p>
            <p>The next in honor is the Font.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes to me an <hi>undecent</hi> thing, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that a Church ſhould have a cover to a Font not worth a groat, not three pence, ſcarce two pence, and that many Fonts ſhould have none at all, but a clamp of rotten boards, or a piece of ſome forlorne table. That the Font ſhould ſtand behinde a Piller, hiding the ſacred action from the Congregation. Since <hi>copula cum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto</hi> is more honourable then <hi>copula cum carne,</hi> &amp; Baptiſme more honorable then Marriage, yet is the ſolemnity of marriage performed in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeſt place, &amp; fulleſt face of the Congregation.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſeems to me a <hi>defective</hi> thing, if not <hi>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> that the whole care of our <hi>Aqua baptiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3084:6"/>ſhould be left to the Clerke, without any other inſpect or over him. Who (having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps but one paile in his houſe, and wanting <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Veſſell to honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9, 21</note> as St. PAVL calls it) ſerves the ſacred Font with the ſame payle with which he ſerves his hog. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perhaps ſnatches up water in his houſe home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed and halfe fouled before, and powres it into a Font more foule than it. Or perhaps commits the whole care of it to his young boy or girle, or takes water ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in the Font before; a moneth, or two moneths, older than the childe.<note place="margin">Carion. an. <hi>743</hi> &amp; an: <hi>978</hi>
               </note> — I dare undertake that thoſe two unhappy Princes, <hi>Conſt. Copr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nymus Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> of <hi>the East,</hi> and <hi>Etheldred King of the Engliſh,</hi> (though the Stories prove true which are reported of them) left as fit behinde them as that which we many times uſe. — I doe not deſire to bring into our Church againe the Papiſt rite of <hi>Exorciſme.</hi> Although I doe not therefore reject it, becauſe it is in their Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for it is nearer us, tis in the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Church,<note place="margin">Eck. ſaſc. <hi>613</hi> Hem Har. lib. <hi>3</hi> part, <hi>2.196.</hi> Eck ſaſek. <hi>615</hi> Aret prob. <hi>197</hi> Kem har. lib. <hi>3</hi> part, <hi>2 196.</hi> Kem. har. lib <hi>3</hi> part, <hi>2 196.</hi> Esk faſch. <hi>613 6.4.</hi>
               </note> and nearer us then ſo, twas in the Primitive Church, in <hi>Cyprian, Nazianzen, Ambroſe, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins</hi> time, though in a better ſenſe then theirs I doubt not. — I doe not think there is <hi>immun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſpiritus</hi> in the water, an uncleane devill to be caſt out by <hi>exorciſme,</hi> but I think there is many times a diveliſh uncleanneſſe, which (ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Ceremonies layd aſide) deſerves to be more reverently avoyded. Since it muſt by and by repreſent the water that came out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3084:7"/>
               <hi>e capſula cordis Chriſti,</hi> and was part of our Redemption, and ſince it muſt by and by be <hi>the one part of an high Sacrament,</hi> even to us <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the laver of a new birth, is St. PAVL to <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It ſeemes to me <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the ancient and pious inſtitution of <hi>Godfathers,</hi> is ſo farre declined from the <hi>gravity</hi> of their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, that young boyes and girles, that have neyther the face nor age of a man,<note place="margin">Nodin Exod. <hi>518.</hi> lin. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere pro ſeipſis,</hi> ſhould <hi>ſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere pro aliis.</hi> — <hi>Beza</hi> (who worthily miſlikes much in <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> the falſely cald <hi>Areopagite</hi>) yet highly comends this in him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bez. vol.</hi> 1.325</note> above all that ever hee read; that he would have Parents deliver their children over, <hi>Praeclaro alicui divinarum rerum doctori</hi> or <hi>informatori,</hi> to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Font, and there to undertake the care of their future Chriſtianity. — His meaning is not that all <hi>Godfathers</hi> ſhould be divines: but his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, that the chiefe ayme of Parents in the choyſe of Godfathers ſhould be, to chuſe able men that could and would. Againe, that thoſe ſhould be no Godfathers, whoſe very face and preſence, puls downe the ſolemnity of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It ſeemes alſo to me an <hi>undecent thing,</hi> that <hi>Godfathers</hi> ſhould decline ſo farre from the primordiall <hi>uſefulneſſe</hi> of their office, and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitablenes</hi> to Chriſtian proficiency. How much
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3084:7"/>increaſe of Religion and good manners (kept they a diligent watch over children in thoſe three parts of their office, which <hi>Dionyſius, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bez. vol. <hi>2.325</hi> Nodin. Exod. <hi>517.</hi> Aq. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>71.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi> ad <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> agree with our Church in) might they bring to the Church. 1 To teach &amp; inſtruct in all fundamentals of Chriſtianity, both for knowledge and life. 2 At every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to perſwade incourage and exhort them. 3 Where they fell ſhort to rebuke and reprove them, and in all theſe to have <hi>diligentem curam &amp; ſollicitudinem continuam.</hi> So ſhould every childe bee under ſome awfull eye where ever he went.<note place="margin">Beza vol. <hi>2.325.</hi> ſin. <hi>326.</hi> init.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> commends the <hi>Geneva</hi> Church that it twice preſſes the Godfather, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after Baptiſme, and makes him twice ſeriouſly to promiſe that he will uſe his beſt care and endeavour, that the childe be brought up in the whole doctrine and law of both Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments: And</p>
            <p n="5">5 It ſeemes to mee an <hi>undecent thing,</hi> that Godfathers undertaking this ſo ſolemnly, in the face of God and his Angels, and in the face of his Congregation, ſhould ſo flight a promiſe made under the eye of ſo great witneſſes. <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tote</hi> ſaith <hi>Aug. vos fidejuſſores pro ipſis apud de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um extitiſse;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nodin. Exod. <hi>517.</hi>
               </note> and ſurely marriage it ſelfe which yet bindes ſo ſtrong, is not undertaken with much more ſolemnitie of promiſes then this office of Godfathers. And thus much of the Font, and ſome undecencies about that.</p>
            <p>And thus have I ſaid all that I meant to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3084:8"/>trouble you with concerning the <hi>Place</hi> of our aſſemblies and of the <hi>vtenſils</hi> of it. I ſhould now lay before your view our <hi>Aſsemblies</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but I would faine have a fit man firſt to cleane the Church, and to ſpeake for them, for when they come they will leave theyr tongues at home.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes to me an <hi>undecent</hi> thing, that our <hi>Clerkes</hi> ſhould be ſcanted in their wages as they are.<note place="margin">The ancient orders wanted good huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract them. <hi>Subdia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conus Acolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus Exorciſta Lector actia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſta.</hi>
               </note> It has beene the good husbandry of rurall Congregations to contract two offices the Clerke and Sextons into one; that that one might have a ſufficient maintainance. After that, to <hi>contract</hi> that one mans wages ſo, that it ſhal not be enough for one; and ſcanty though it be, yet more ſcantily ſhall it be payd. For they being in their originall an Eccleſiaſticall Order conſtituted by Byſhops as we are, their meanes alſo was a kinde of Church mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. As they deale with the Miniſter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his portion, no marvaile if they deale ſo with the Clerke in his; and let him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine if he dare.<note place="margin">Math. 10, 24</note> For the Diſciple is ſeldome above his Maſter.— Along with the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction</hi> of niggardize, has gone the <hi>contraction</hi> of times; For their meanes being neither prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall nor perſonall Tithes, but a bare ſtipend of ſo many pence by the yeare; the greater price things beare the fewer will their purſe reach too; and the more muſt they be content to want. For a penny will never be more then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3084:8"/>a penny; but a penny-worth will in time grow to be worth a ſhilling. The Clerke has ſtill but his penny to buy that ſhillings worth, and ſo have the times ſwept away eleven parts of 12. of his maintenance, and it ſhall goe hard but his Pariſh will ſweepe away a quarter of that too, his penny ſhall be but three farthings, perhaps a halfe penny. Hence come they to be men of ſo meane parts as they are, ſcarce <hi>Organa</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo meane God wot in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts of the Church, that they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doe the Clerkly part of their office, to anſwer the reſponſories without blaſphemie. — An undecent thing I ſay it is, that theſe ſhould be ſo ſcanted for wages, ſince the clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of our Churches, depends upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the worke: and ſince the ſufficiencie of the man is not bought but by the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the wages, and ſince every workman (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the moſt dunghill labourer) is worthy of his hyer. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.7. And now will I ſhew you our <hi>Aſsemblies</hi> and the parts in them.</p>
            <p>The parts and parties are Men, Women and Children, <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.16. For it ſeemes to me an undecent thing, that any that has a reaſonable ſoule <hi>(actu primo &amp; ſecundo reaſonable)</hi> ſhould exempt himſelfe when Gods reaſonable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, is a doing.<note place="margin">Rom. 12, 1</note> — And it ſeemes to me a more undecent thing, that any that has not a reaſonable ſoule, (neyther
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3084:9"/>
               <hi>actu primo</hi> nor <hi>ſecundo</hi> reaſonable) ſhould fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent when Gods reaſonable ſervice is a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. — I muſt therefore crave pardon while I reckon up <hi>(pax ſit auribus &amp; ſuggeſto ſalus)</hi> dogs among the parts of our Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Shall I call it no more then <hi>a diſorder,</hi> that the Conſecrated bread even then when the Prieſt is adminiſtring it and ſaying take eate, ſhould be to be taken up from under the feet, and that flung downe by the diſturbance of Dogs? — 2 That Dogs ſhould be about the Font, under his feet betweene his legs as he is adminiſtring the ſacred Baptiſme? — 3 Shall I call it but a diſorder, that dogs are ſeen in the face of the Congregation (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Bitchering, others ſmelling out a ſeate to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſſe, and in their courſes doe it? <hi>Non ſunt haec ficta ſed facta,</hi> I faine them not. I have noted the dayes <hi>nigro</hi> θ. Are theſe the <hi>omnia bene</hi> of our Churchwardens bils? — I ſay nothing of their frequent barkings, brawlings and figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; the breaking off of <hi>divina officia</hi> till they have done: becauſe theſe are ſmal things. When the <hi>Oſliarii Tabernaculi</hi> did their office accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods owne Booke of Canons, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.18. a Dog might not be ſuffered to come into the Tabernacle, no not the hire of a dog. No not the hire of a dog in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Kem. Harm. l. <hi>1.279.</hi>
               </note> the popular place of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, much leſſe in <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum.</hi> None ought to have a place in the Church, who are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3084:9"/>not capable of a place in heaven, becauſe the Church is a ſchoole to heaven. But leave wee dogs to their proper place <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.15. Let all Dogs be without, &amp; all Chriſtians within: And to their proper worke, <hi>Excubare per re Domini,</hi> as <hi>Livie</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Livius</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>lin.</hi> 33. <hi>Stack: tom.</hi> 2.46. <hi>pag</hi> 2.</note> Let them watch at home while their Maſters wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſeemes to me <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That the Miniſter ſhould ſit, after the bels have don, and the bookes laid halfe an houre, 3. quarters of an houre, before he can have a company, that ſhall beare the face of a Congregation; in the meane time the Church-yard hath his ſeverall confabulations, conſultations and deambulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his laughings, leapings and ſhoutings. — An undecent thing I ſay, ſince it is the office of Bels to make them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; That is to call them out of Houſes, Streets, Fields, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards and all places into Churches.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It ſeemes to me an <hi>undecent thing,</hi> That if the Miniſter begin at his appointed time or ſoone after the laſt toll: halfe prayers, nay 3 quarters ſhould be don, ſermon begun, before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation meet. Since the firſt part of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy is as acceptable to God as the middle and end. And ſince hee never in any undertaking makes a good end, that leaves out the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or middle. —</p>
            <p n="4">4 It ſeems to me an <hi>undecent</hi> thing, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> halfe divine Service is loſt for want of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3084:10"/>the reſt ſhould be loſt for want of auditors. My meaning is, the claſhing of Pattens in the porches; and the clamping of nailed ſhooes on the pavements of the Church; the ruſling up of thoſe who are already kneel'd to make way for them that come late, to come to their ſeates, do ſo cry down for half an houre together the reſt of the Liturgy, that thoſe that ſhould be audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are but images, they have eares to heare but heare not. An <hi>undecent</hi> thing I ſay, Since divine ſervice ought to be free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſturbance as wel of walking as of talking. <hi>Canon,</hi> 18.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It ſeemes to me an <hi>undecent</hi> thing, and not only <hi>deordinatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> but <hi>deordinans,</hi> a cauſe of much diſorder; That in Pariſhes where there are that come not to Church in 6 weekes, 8 weekes, 18 weeks together, being able perſons. That in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes where there are young ones of 12, or 14 yeares of age which never yet came in Church but once, <hi>viz.</hi> on the day of their Baptiſme. Yet our Church-wardens ſhould give up bils with <hi>Omnia bene.</hi> An <hi>undecent</hi> thing I ſay, ſince the Courts of reformation are the immediate inſtruments of GOD by which he keepes his Church in decency &amp; order. And ſince Oathes there given are the ſtrongeſt inſtruments of Courts.<note place="margin">Eraſm. Ling. <hi>95.</hi>
               </note>—Since the greateſt ſinne (next to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy) which the tongue can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit is Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and the greateſt perjury, is perjury before a rightfull Iudge ſitting in <hi>actu judicativo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 It ſeems to me an <hi>undecent</hi> thing, That young boyes of 14, and 16 yeares of age ſhould
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3084:10"/>ſit covered while the Preacher is delivering to him Gods meſſage.<note place="margin">Kem. Harm. l. <hi>4.</hi> part <hi>1.138.</hi>
               </note> Since <hi>potiores ſunt partes docentis quam diſcentis &amp; ſedere &amp; cooperire</hi> is the proper <hi>ſitus &amp; habitus docentis.</hi> And ſince the ſonne owes this to his Father; and the ſervant to his maſter; and the inferiors to the heads of the Congregation, not to ſit covered at ſo ſmall a a diſtance.</p>
            <p n="7">7 It ſeems to me an <hi>undecent thing.</hi> That Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners ſhould teach the Miniſter another me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of care of ſoules then the Canons doe. That he ſhould leave out a leſſon, with the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle and Goſpell, the Letanie and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that they may have Sermon enough.— Since the Leſſons Epiſtles and Goſpels, are <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum Dei</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but a Sermon is but <hi>verbum dei</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> at the moſt; and I would to God that thoſe Sermons which ſuch men ſo much glote after, and preferre ſo farre before Leſſons, Epiſtles and Goſpels, were alway ſo much.</p>
            <p n="8">8 It ſeemes to me an <hi>undecent</hi> thing, That in a Pariſh of Three or 400 people, there ſhould not be found three beſide the Clerke, that anſwer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to our Prayers or make any <hi>reſponſorie</hi> to the Commandements or other parts of the Liturgy. And that ſelfe-conceited man,<note place="margin">Kem. Harm. l. <hi>2.136.</hi>
               </note> his braines ſtood certainly the backſide forward, that acquitted himſelfe and his Sect of their lip-labour thus. How ſhould a man ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not; the plainneſſe of our prayers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him rather of Schiſme and obſtinacie than
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3084:11"/>of ignorance.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Canon.</hi> 8.</note> — An <hi>undecent</hi> thing I ſay, Since the <hi>Amen</hi> of the mouth is as due as the <hi>Amen</hi> of the heart; if both need both muſt aske, if both receive both muſt give thankes. Since in the times of the Church nearer CHRIST, the whole people, not onely the Clerke anſwered <hi>Amen</hi> to the Church prayers. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (ſaith <hi>Iuſtin Mart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bl.</hi> 227.</note>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And that not with whiſpering or mumbling, but <hi>fauſta acclamatione,</hi> with a ſhouting voice, a voyce of men ſhewing how they favoured them, conſented to them, and deſired they ſhould proſper.<note n="*" place="margin">Nonnius Marcellus.</note> 
               <hi>Fauſtus a faven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</hi> — Yea ſince even in the Churches trained up under the Apoſtles themſelves, All the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaid <hi>Amen.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. tom</hi> 3.48<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>How ſhall hee that occupies the roome of the unlearned ſay Amen at the giving of thanks.</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16.) — Yea ſince the light of nature teaches as much, for thence <hi>Epicletus</hi> had it. If I were a <hi>Nightingale</hi> (ſayth hee) I would doe as a <hi>Nightingale,</hi> but being a man I will doe as a man. I will not be all voyce, for thats like a bird, too low, nor all ſpirit for thats like an Angell too high for me; but ſpirit and voyce thats like a Man, I will keep my ranke. — And <hi>Conſtantine the Great</hi> (whoſe memory ought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to bee honourable in the Church) would not onely ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to the prayers, but would reade the verſes of the Pſalmes interchangeably with the Miniſter,<note n="*" place="margin">S D. <hi>185</hi>
               </note> ſayth <hi>Euſeb in. vit. Conſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 It ſeemes to me <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a diſorder, That
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3084:11"/>Pariſhioners ſhould throng by Thirties and by forties to other Churches and leave their owne empty. That a ſicke party ſhould ſend to the next Pariſh to bee prayed for; That another on his death-bed, ſhould ſend for the ſame Miniſter home to him to viſit him, to pray with him, to Preach for him. In the mean time the proper Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, to whom God and the Church hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the care of his ſoule, though hee offer his ſervice ſhall not be accepted; though he offer to Preach, there ſhall be no Sermon rather. What is this, but for the people to uſurp Epiſcopall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? To ſet over themſelves what paſtor they pleaſe? nay more then Epiſcopall authority. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every vaine fancie to choſe, upon every vaine fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh to leave their choiſe. In thoſe ancient Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches where (by connivence not of right) the people had a hand in the choyſe of their Paſtor, yet when they had choſen they were no more at liberty to leave them. Even in St. <hi>Iohns</hi> time, though Pariſhes were not yet divided. As the 7 Angels had their ſeverall Churches; ſo thoſe 7. Churches had their ſeverall Angels. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.20.</p>
            <p n="10">10 It ſeemed to me an <hi>undecent</hi> ſpeech, his brains ſure had no <hi>Pia mater,</hi> that ſpoke it. I heard (ſayth one) a Preacher, and he ſpake for the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the name of IESVS, he was fitter to preach in a tub then in a pulpit. — An <hi>undecent</hi> ſpeech I ſay; Since not only the Reverend Fathers of our Church, (whoſe learned and pious Sermons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for them (I am ſure) better then a Tub to preach in) doe ſpeake for it in their Canons: but<note place="margin">a <hi>Hoker,</hi> 347. <hi>Bell. to.</hi> 2.246</note>
               <note place="margin">b <hi>Aret. Probl.</hi> 189 <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note>
               <note place="margin">c <hi>Hoker,</hi> 433. Canon 18.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3084:12"/>alſo ancient Fathers the honour of Pulpits for their times, do yet ſpeake for it in their writings: writings not bung'd up in bartels, nor tumbled into cubs, but writings which are counted the ornaments of the greateſt Libraries in the world. And he whoſe writings are in the moſt Preachers hand in this land (who are worthily famous for preaching) and are many a time the credit of their beſt ſermons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stell Luc.</hi> 10.1.67. <hi>coll.</hi> 1.</note> thinks this fit for a Pulpit not for a Tub. The name IESUS (ſaith he) of all his names coſt him deareſt, the name God he has fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his nature; the name LORD from his power; the name CHRIST from his unction, &amp;c. they coſt him no ſhame, no teares, no trouble, no bloud; the name IESUS or <hi>Saviour</hi> coſt him his bloud. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by his blood.</hi> On the Croſſe he ſaved us, on the croſſe (by divine providence) was no other name. <hi>This is Ieſus the King of the Iewes. Mat.</hi> 27 33 — If <hi>Chriſt</hi> be God and man doe we amiſſe to bow to him? If we doe not amiſſe in bowing to him, doe we amiſſe in taking that time to bow to him whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his name is named? Few prayers in our Liturgy are made to <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. to.</hi> 3.847 † 84<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but to the father in <hi>Chriſts</hi> name, and are concluded for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſuite is made, to him is the bowing; not to him directly in whoſe name tis made. If we adde ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this decent ceremony to his direct worſhip, will not a little patience be enough to beare it? If he like not our ceremony, nor liſt not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe to it, yet let him yeild us the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of St. <hi>Iames</hi> prohibition, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3084:12"/>— Let him ſhew me, that 'tis either <hi>contra fidem,</hi> or <hi>contra bonos mores,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>8.</hi> K <hi>56.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>11</hi> ſ, ad Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arium.</note> and as St. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith, and I will juſtle with our Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it an no longer obey; which till he can do, let the Philoſophers ambition be his wiſdome; who when every man was eager to ſhew his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and to have it recorded as <hi>concluſum eſt,</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that this only might be recorded of him.<note place="margin">Advancem. l. <hi>2 106</hi> pa.</note> 
               <hi>That there was one there, that knew how to hold his peace,</hi> — which is time for me to doe.</p>
            <p>I will adde only this one thing, for the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of outward decency an order. — It is neceſſary it ſhould be ſeene, there is a God in the world. — This cannot be ſeen by his eſſence, though it fill the world. — It cannot be ſeene by the hearts of men, they are as hidden fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our eye as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. — In the book of nature he has too much hid himſelf from the people eye. — Therefore there need other outward expreſſions of him, which the people are capable of, <hi>viz</hi> our outward aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies, the places of them, and our carriages in them; all which ought to be ſuch, as may convey a revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t opinion of him into the peoples hart by the eye.</p>
            <p>If it be neceſſary God ſhould be ſeene in the world, tis neceſſary he ſhould be ſeen as he is. Not only that he is a <hi>God</hi> of holines, but alſo that he is a <hi>God</hi> of majeſty. To this <hi>Chriſt</hi> directs us. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing your good works, may <hi>glorifie</hi> your father w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is in heaven; he would have not only our <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin,</hi> but our <hi>outward works,</hi> to direct men to this, that <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>glorious God,</hi> &amp; therfore to be <hi>glorified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3084:13"/>
If any outward works of man do report <hi>Gods</hi> majeſty to the world, then ſurely theſe; the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>houſes</hi> for him, the frequenting of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the cariages of men in them; for theſe are directly to that end to report <hi>God.</hi> The more directly they are to that end, the more lively they ought to do it, &amp; <hi>pro poſſe,</hi> leſt they report ſhort, and make him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalued. — <hi>Outward cariage</hi> therefore and ſpeech, as well of the aſſembly as of the Prieſt ought to report home.</p>
            <p>And for our Temples and the utenſils of them, God himſelfe directs us.</p>
            <p>When he platform'd out his own Tabernacle &amp; inſpired <hi>Solomon</hi> to his own Temple, we ſee how glorious they were. Not only the buildings, but even the loweſt utenſils, the ſnuffers and ſnuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhes did <hi>pro poſſe praeſe ferre-numen,</hi> all of pure gold. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 7.49.</p>
            <p>Though we are not bound to take this as a law from God, to make all our Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples by; yet we ſhal do wel to make him our pattern. At leaſt to learn thence, what manner of Temples diſtaſt him not. And if we acquit our ſelves from the coſtlines &amp; gloriouſnes; yet may we not free our ſelves from the decency &amp; comelines. Though <hi>God</hi> ſhun not a <hi>cottage,</hi> yet <hi>men</hi> muſt think him <hi>worthy</hi> of a <hi>palace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I laid before this <hi>Synod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> thoſe things which I thought differ'd from St. <hi>Pauls</hi> rule, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>If I have ſpoken that which is pleaſing in his eyes, the Lord proſper it and carry it on; if otherwiſe, the Lord amend it, and there end it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed are they which heare the word of God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3084:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
